Samantha M Schaevitz

Contact

Zürich, Switzerland

samanthaschaevitz.com

samschaevitz@gmail.com

Profile

Principal software engineer with a decade+ of experience in leading technical organizations as they build and operate innovative planet-scale systems with a high level of reliability. Currently the Area Tech Lead for Workspace (4K+ engineers) Production & Reliability, and the most senior individual contributor and only Principal Engineer in Google Workspace's Site Reliability Engineering organization (185+ engineers). Recent focus on data sovereignty, capacity efficiency & automation, and automated fleet (1K+ nodes) management.

Professional Experience

Google Principal Engineer - Workspace

2013-12 - Present

Area Tech Lead for Workspace (Gmail, Drive, Meet, Calendar, Chat, etc. with 3B+ users, 6M+ paid customers) production & reliability. Hired as an L3 Software Engineer, I have been promoted in this role 5 times – most recently in 2023. I set the technical bar for the organization, broker decisions where there is paralysis, work cross-functionally beyond Workspace with the rest of Google, and grow and mentor the bench of staff+ technical leaders in the organization, in addition to trailblazing and delivering technical contributions:

- Reduced production cost, capacity outages, and manual operational work through strategy development, x-org alignment, and lead a core team of 5+ engineers to safely & efficiently onboard 1K+ services in a 4K+ person organization to our capacity automation platform
- Improved production standards (e.g. safe deployment practices, compliance commitments, AAA hygiene, etc.) adoption, regression, and remediation across the 4K+-engineering organization by developing continuous fleet validation & reporting infrastructure
- Developed and co-authored the CEO of Google Cloud-approved technical strategy for the business' next-gen data sovereignty strategy, through cross-functional collaboration with PM leadership, systems analysis, and targeted prototyping
- Reduced user-visible outages caused by confusing and complicated network configuration by finding x-organizational alignment to refocus the Google network organization on the needs of Workspace services
- Kept Google Meet capacity ahead of user demand during the early months of the COVID19 pandemic (see publications)
- Owned and developed the production strategy for the migration of Google Calendar to an entirely new storage system, which took place without incident
- Reduced stuck rollouts, operational load of tool management, and cognitive load of varied procedures of Gmail's binary release process (30+ services) by developing and migrating to next-gen intent-driven rollout infrastructure

Internal Technology Resident in Corporate Operations Engineering

2012 - 08 - 2013 - 12

• Built software to make Support at Google run more efficiently and effectively, including a Python server run on App Engine to generate acceptable schedules for the global support organization

UC Berkeley ResComp Unit Supervisor, Consultant

2009 - 08 - 2012 - 05

- Supervised a team of four Residential Computing Consultants (RCCs) responsible for technical support services
- Enacted networking, security, and peripheral troubleshooting and configuration tactics to resolve software and hardware problems for 1000+ students living in residence halls

Publications

StaffPlus London: The Dark Side of Standardization (June 2023)

USENIX SREcon: Scaling for a Pandemic: How We Keep Ahead of Demand for Google Meet during COVID-19 (October 2021)

StaffPlus Live: How We've Scaled Meet During COVID19 (September 2021)

All Day DevOps: How We Scaled Google Meet during COVID19 (November 2020)

Google Workspace Blog: Three months, 30x demand: How we scaled Google Meet during COVID-19 (August 2020)

USENIX SREcon: Deploying Changes to Production in the Age of the Microservice (August 2017)

Education University of California, Berkeley

2008-08 - 2012-05

Bachelor of Arts in Computer Science, French Language Minor

COMMUNITY

${\bf HURIDOCS}\ \mathit{Full-Stack}\ \mathit{Developer}$

 $\mathbf{2019}\text{-}\mathbf{09} - \mathbf{2020}\text{-}\mathbf{03}$

• Significantly improved human rights data curation throughput by developing and productionizing a machine-learning based suggestion agent

NetHope, Slovenia Network Operations Engineer, Electrician

2015-12

• Surveyed and deployed 10+ wireless networks and 20+ charging stations at 3 refugee accommodations (5000+ refugee capacity)

LANGUAGES English, French, German

ACTIVITIES The Zoogler Orchestra (Flute Section), traveling (30+ countries), alpine sports (skiing, hiking, lake swimming, etc.)